<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37046209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10091330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12883-023-03176-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on neuropsychiatric and sleep disorders, and quality of life in individuals with neurodegenerative and demyelinating diseases: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Marcos Paulo Braz</given-names></name><address><email>marcospbraz@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>Ana Emilia Fonseca</given-names></name><address><email>anaemiliafcastro@yahoo.com.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miri</surname><given-names>Andressa Leticia</given-names></name><address><email>andressamiri@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>Carla Rigo</given-names></name><address><email>clima@uab.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Truax</surname><given-names>Brendon David</given-names></name><address><email>brendontruax2@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>Vanessa Suziane</given-names></name><address><email>vanessaprobst@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smaili</surname><given-names>Suhaila Mahmoud</given-names></name><address><email>suhaila@uel.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411247.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2163 588X</institution-id><institution>Healthy Aging Research Laboratory, Department of Physical Therapy, </institution><institution>Federal University of S&#x000e3;o Carlos, </institution></institution-wrap>Washington Luis Highway, Km 235, S&#x000e3;o Carlos S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411087.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 2494</institution-id><institution>Physical Therapy Laboratory, Department of Physical Therapy, </institution><institution>State University of Campinas, </institution></institution-wrap>S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Campinas Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411400.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 3537</institution-id><institution>Neurofunctional Physical Therapy Research Group, Department of Physical Therapy, </institution><institution>State University of Londrina, </institution></institution-wrap>Londrina, Paran&#x000e1; Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000106344187</institution-id><institution>Mechanisms of Spinal Manual Therapy Laboratory, Department of Physical Therapy, </institution><institution>The University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>Birmingham, AL USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265892.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000106344187</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care, </institution><institution>The University of Alabama at Birmingham, </institution></institution-wrap>Birmingham, AL USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>150</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has affected the mental health, sleep and quality of life, especially in individuals with chronic disease. Therefore, the purpose of this systematic review and meta-analysis was to investigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on neuropsychiatric disorders (depression, anxiety, stress), sleep disorders (sleep quality, insomnia) and quality of life in individuals with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease (PD), Multiple Sclerosis (MS) and Alzheimer's disease (AD) compared to healthy controls.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Seven databases (Medline, Embase, ScienceDirect, Web of Science, The Cochrane Library, Scielo and Lilacs) were searched between March 2020 and December 2022. Observational studies (i.e., cross-sectional, case&#x02013;control, cohort) were included. GRADE approach was used to assess the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation. Effect size was calculated using standardized mean differences (SMD; random effects model). A customized Downs and Black checklist was used to assess the risk of bias.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Eighteen studies (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;7, MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;11) were included. A total of 627 individuals with PD (healthy controls&#x02009;=&#x02009;857) and 3923 individuals with MS (healthy controls&#x02009;=&#x02009;2432) were analyzed. Twelve studies (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;4, MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) were included in the meta-analysis. Individuals with PD had significantly elevated levels of depression (very low evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04) and stress (very low evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). There was no difference in anxiety (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.08). Individuals with MS had significantly higher levels of depression (very low evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007) and stress (low evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03) and low quality of life (very low evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006). There was no difference in anxiety (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05) and sleep quality (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13). It was not possible to synthesize evidence in individuals with AD and sleep disorder (insomnia).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">In general, the COVID-19 pandemic negatively impacted individuals with PD and MS. Individuals with PD showed significantly higher levels of depression and stress; and individuals with MS presented significantly higher depression and stress levels, as well as significantly lower quality of life when compared to healthy controls. Further studies are needed to investigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with AD.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Parkinson disease</kwd><kwd>Multiple sclerosis</kwd><kwd>Alzheimer disease</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Systematic review</kwd><kwd>Meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par22">Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). On January 30, 2020, the World Health Organization declared COVID-19 an international public health emergency quickly escalating to a global pandemic on March 11, 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Individuals with chronic diseases are the most vulnerable to infectious diseases such as COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Among the chronic diseases that affect the central nervous system, Parkinson's disease (PD), Multiple Sclerosis (MS) and Alzheimer's disease (AD) are the most common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. These diseases present varied epidemiology, clinical symptomatology, laboratory and neuroimaging characteristics, neuropathology and management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">The neuropathology of PD is characterized by the progressive loss of dopaminergic neurons of the substantia nigra in the midbrain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. MS is a chronic immuno-mediated inflammatory condition that affects the central nervous system as a consequence of the infiltration of self-reactive lymphocytes into the blood brain barrier, causing local inflammation that results in demyelination, glial scar formation and axonal loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. AD is marked by the formation of beta-amyloid protein plaques and tangles of tau proteins in neurons located in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. It is important to highlight that the neuropathology underlying these conditions has been associated to a greater vulnerability to SARS-CoV-2 infection and the development of COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Despite the differences in the underlying neuropathology, these conditions share common characteristics such as the presence of neuropsychiatric disorders (anxiety, depression, and stress), sleep disorders (bad sleep and insomnia) and low quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. These propensities were further exacerbated during the COVID-19 pandemic with healthcare efforts being shifted from treating chronic illness towards prevention and management of SARS-CoV-2; consequently, having a negative impact on their mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">The shift observed in the healthcare system increased the likelihood for these individuals to develop, relapse or aggravate neuropsychiatric and sleep disorders potentially leading to a lower quality of life. Abasiyanik, Kurt and Kahraman (2022) have contributed to furthering the scientific knowledge surrounding the impact of COVID-19 on various neurological conditions within their systematic review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Though, a few notable limitations were present within this review such as: quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation were not assessed; a meta-analysis was not performed making effect size estimation challenging; and the clinical heterogeneity between the observational studies was not reported.</p><p id="Par26">To encourage evidence-based practice in informed decision-making regarding the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with PD, MS, and AD, additional systematic review studies with more rigorous methodology are needed. Therefore, the purpose of this systematic review and meta-analysis was to investigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on 1) neuropsychiatric disorders (depression, anxiety, and stress), 2) sleep disorders (sleep quality and insomnia) and 3) quality of life in individuals with PD, MS and AD compared to healthy controls.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par27">This systematic review and meta-analysis followed the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines and the recommendations from the Cochrane Collaboration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation was assessed by the Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The protocol was registered in the International Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews (PROSPERO) (CRD42021286219).</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Search strategy</title><p id="Par28">The electronic search was performed in seven databases (Medline, Embase, ScienceDirect, Web of Science, The Cochrane Library, Scielo and Lilacs) between March 2020 and December 2022, using the following combination of keywords: (Parkinson Disease OR Alzheimer Disease OR Multiple Sclerosis) AND (depression OR anxiety OR stress OR sleep OR insomnia OR quality of life) AND (COVID-19). The search string was composed of keywords selected from the Medical Subjects Headings controlled vocabulary.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p id="Par29">Observational studies (i.e., cross-sectional, case&#x02013;control, and cohort) were included. For the inclusion criteria, the patient, intervention, comparison, and outcome (PICO) strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] was utilized being 1) (P) Patient: individuals with neurodegenerative and demyelinating diseases (PD, MS, and AD); 2) (I) Intervention: studies conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic regardless of peak contamination, social distancing and quarantine; 3) (C) Comparison: healthy controls, and 4) (O) Outcomes: neuropsychiatric disorders (depression, anxiety, and stress), sleep disorders (sleep quality, and insomnia), and quality of life. Studies using evaluation scales with confirmed psychometric properties (reliability, validity or responsiveness) were included and domain or total scores of these scales were considered. Only full publications in English, Spanish and Portuguese were included. Exclusion criteria included 1) studies that used qualitative data, 2) control groups with other neurodegenerative and/or neurological diseases, 3) studies comparing specific moments of the COVID-19 pandemic (before and during), and 4) intragroup or association analyses (regression).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Selection process</title><p id="Par30">Title, abstract and full text screenings were conducted by two independent reviewers (M. P. B. O. and C. R. L.) following the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The reference lists of included studies were manually searched to identify possible titles not recovered in the initial electronic searches. Any disagreements in the selection process were resolved by consensus. When consensus was not reached, a third reviewer (S. M. S.) was consulted. The State of the Art through Systematic Review reference manager software was used for the screening process and title selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data extraction</title><p id="Par31">An adapted form from the Cochrane Collaboration was implemented for data extraction of the included studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Data variables included the study period, data collection procedures, recruitment of individuals, country, and continent. For the neurodegenerative and demyelinating disease group, the type of population, diagnostic criteria, sample size, mean age, and gender were extracted. For the healthy control group, sample size, mean age, and gender were extracted. The outcomes, evaluation scales, and statistical results (<italic>p</italic>-value) of the studies were also recorded. Effect sizes and 95% confidence intervals (CI) were calculated considering the sample size, mean, and standard deviation values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation assessment: GRADE</title><p id="Par32">The GRADE approach was used to assess the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This approach considers five criteria: limitations (risk of bias), inconsistency, indirectness, imprecision, and publication bias. The studies by comparison group met the limitations criterion when they reached&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;9 points (&#x02265;&#x02009;66.8%) of the total score on the custom checklist of Downs and Black [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The interpretation of these criteria allows classifying the evidence as high, moderate, low or very low. It is important to highlight that when observational studies are considered for evidence synthesis, the quality of evidence begins as low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par33">The studies included in the meta-analysis were grouped based on the outcomes evaluated. The effect size was calculated using standardized mean differences (SMD) with 95% CI. Mean and standard deviation values were used. The effect size was considered significant when the <italic>p-value</italic> was less than 0.05 (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and classified as small (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.20), moderate (between 0.21 and 0.79) or large (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.80) effect size based on Cohen's criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Given the variability of the effect size among the included studies, the random effects model was used. Index <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> was used to evaluate the heterogeneity among the studies included in the meta-analysis and interpreted as small (&#x02264;&#x02009;25%), moderate (between 26 and 74%) or large (&#x02265;&#x02009;75%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The statistical tools of the Review Manager software (RevMan version 5.4.1) were used.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Risk of bias assessment: customized downs and black checklist</title><p id="Par34">A customized checklist was developed to assess the risk of bias of the included studies through the scale proposed by Downs and Black [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. This scale was developed to assess randomized and non-randomized studies. The original version has five domains and 27 items: reporting (1&#x02013;10), external validity (11&#x02013;13), internal validity&#x02014;bias (14&#x02013;20), internal validity&#x02014;selection bias (21&#x02013;26) and power (27). The customized Downs and Black checklist of this systematic review and meta-analysis was developed including four domains and 13 items: reporting (1&#x02013;3, 6, 7, 9, 10), external validity (11), internal validity&#x02014;bias (18, 20), internal validity&#x02014;selection bias (21, 22, 26). The remaining items on the checklist did not apply to observational studies and therefore were excluded. The responses on the 13 selected items were scored as 0 (no or unable to determine) or 1 (yes) based on the original version with the maximum possible score being 13. Risk of bias associated with each study was classified as low (&#x02265;&#x02009;9 points [&#x02265;&#x02009;66.8%]), moderate (between 5 and 8 points (33.4 to 66.7%) or high (&#x02264;&#x02009;4 points [&#x02264;&#x02009;33.3%]) by two independent reviewers (A. E. F. C. and A. L. M.) with a third reviewer (M. P. B. O.) being consulted in case of disagreements. This model of personalization and classification of the risk of bias has been previously reported in a systematic review and meta-analysis in individuals with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><p id="Par35">The initial electronic search retrieved 3489 references with no additional studies being retrieved via manual search. After the screening process, 18 studies were included. Seven studies in individuals with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and 11 studies in individuals with MS were identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. No study was identified in individuals with AD. Twelve studies (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;four and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) were included in the meta-analysis. The study selection flowchart of the systematic review and meta-analysis is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of studies selection process. (PD) Parkinson&#x02019;s disease; (MS) Multiple Sclerosis; (AD) Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2023_3176_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par36">Fifteen studies were conducted in 2020 (March to December) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], a study in 2021 (January to February) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] and two studies did not report this information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Data collection procedures were performed by phone, e-mail or online in 14 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]; in person interviews in one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]; and three studies did not report this information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Fifteen studies recruited individuals in specific sites (hospitals, laboratory databases, clinics or treatment centers) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]&#x000a0;and three studies in non-specific web-based sites (social networks [e.g., facebook or Instagram] and personal communications) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The studies were conducted in 10 different countries (China, Egypt, Italy, Iran, Japan, New Zealand, Republic of Serbia, Turkey, United Kingdom and United States) covering five continents (Africa, Asia, Europe, North America and Oceania). Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents the main characteristics of the included studies.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Authors (year)</th><th align="left">Study period<break/>Data collection procedure<break/>Recruitment of participants<break/>Country<break/>Continent(s)</th><th align="left">Diseases<break/>Population<break/>Diagnostic criteria<break/>Sample size, n<break/>Age, mean<break/>Sex, female / male</th><th align="left">Health controls<break/>Sample size, n<break/>Age, mean<break/>Sex, female / male</th><th align="left">(1) Neuropsychiatric disorders, (2) Sleep disorders and (3) Quality of life<break/>Outcome(s) / Tool(s) / <italic>p</italic>-value / Effect size (95% confidence interval)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Balci et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between March to June 2020</p><p>Phone</p><p>Laboratory database</p><p>Turkey</p><p>Europe and Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>UKPDSBB</p><p>45</p><p>67.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>15 female; 30 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>43</p><p>66.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>19 female; 24 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / HADS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.524 / -</p><p>(1) Anxiety / HADS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.977 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Blakemore et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between April to May 2020</p><p>Phone or online</p><p>Laboratory database (New Zealand Brain Research Institute)</p><p>New Zealand</p><p>Oceania</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>-</p><p>149</p><p>72.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>-</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>51</p><p>78.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>-</p></td><td align="left">(1) Stress / PSS / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;99% / 0.55 (0.23 to 0.88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Kitani-Morii et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between April to May 2020</p><p>Phone or e-mail</p><p>University Hospital, Kyoto Prefectural University of Medicine</p><p>Japan</p><p>Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>-</p><p>39</p><p>72.3&#x000a0;years</p><p>14 female; 25 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>32</p><p>66.4&#x000a0;years</p><p>27 female; 5 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / PHQ / <italic>p</italic> 0.010 / -</p><p>(1) Anxiety / GAD / <italic>p</italic> 0.130 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Insomnia / ISI / <italic>p</italic> 0.170 / -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Suzuki et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between June to December 2020</p><p>-</p><p>Dokkyo Medical University Hospital</p><p>Japan</p><p>Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>MDS</p><p>100</p><p>72.2&#x000a0;years</p><p>55 female, 45 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>100</p><p>65.5&#x000a0;years</p><p>53 female; 47 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / HADS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.585 / -</p><p>(1) Anxiety / HADS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 1.000 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / SF-8-<italic>physical function</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -0.63 (-0.92 to -0.35); SF-8-<italic>role physical</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -0.54 (-0.82 to -0.26); SF-8-<italic>bodily pain</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.055 / -0.27 (-0.55 to 0.01); SF-8-<italic>general health</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / -0.49 (-0.78 to -0.21); SF-8-vitality / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -0.61 (-0.90 to -0.33); SF-8-<italic>social functioning</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.949 / -0.01 (-0.29 to 0.27); SF-8-<italic>role emotional</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.490 / -0.09 (-0.37 to 0.19); SF-8-<italic>mental health</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.804 / -0.04 (-0.32 to 0.23); SF-8-<italic>physical component</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -0.72 (-1.00 to -0.43); SF-8-<italic>mental component</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.349 / 0.13 (-0.15 to 0.40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Salari et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>-</p><p>Online</p><p>Movement Disorders Center</p><p>Iran</p><p>Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>-</p><p>137</p><p>55.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>90 female; 47 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>442</p><p>-</p><p>-</p></td><td align="left">(1) Anxiety / BAI-II / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 1.04 (0.84 to 1.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Shalash et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>-</p><p>Phone</p><p>Ain Shams University Hospitals</p><p>Egypt</p><p>Africa and Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>-</p><p>38</p><p>55.6&#x000a0;years</p><p>9 female; 29 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>20</p><p>55.5&#x000a0;years</p><p>6 female; 14 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / DASS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.015 / 0.68 (0.12 to 1.24)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / DASS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / 0.84 (0.27 to 1.40)</p><p>(1) Stress / DASS-<italic>stress</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.028 / 0.62 (0.06 to 1.17)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / PDQ-39 / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 0.85 (0.29 to 1.42)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Xia et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>April 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Neurology clinic in Wuhan</p><p>China</p><p>Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>PD</p><p>UKPDSBB</p><p>119</p><p>61.2&#x000a0;years</p><p>58 female; 61 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>169</p><p>59.8&#x000a0;years</p><p>93 female; 76 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / HADS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.022 / 0.27 (0.03 to 0.51)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / HADS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.579 / 0.07 (-0.16 to 0.31)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Sleep quality / PSQI / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 0.74 (0.50 to 0.98)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Goverover et al. 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between July to October 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Web-based (unspecific)</p><p>United States</p><p>North America</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>69</p><p>48.1&#x000a0;years</p><p>- (unclear information)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>95</p><p>42.9&#x000a0;years</p><p>79 female; 16 male</p></td><td align="left">(1) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / FACT-7 / p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 1.07 (0.74 to 1.40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Koc et al. 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between January to February 2021</p><p>Face-to-face interviews</p><p>Neurology Clinic of Uludag University, Faculty of Medicine</p><p>Turkey</p><p>Europe and Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>86</p><p>38.1&#x000a0;years</p><p>57 female; 29 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>65</p><p>38.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>43 femanle; 22 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / BDI / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -</p><p>(1) Anxiety / BAI / <italic>p</italic> 0.010 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Sleep quality / PSQI / <italic>p</italic> 0.731 / -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / SF-36-<italic>physical functioning</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -; SF-36-<italic>physical role limitations</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / -; SF-36-<italic>emotional role limitations</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.080 / -; SF-36-<italic>vitality</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.010 / -; SF-36-<italic>emotional well-being</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.055 / -; SF-36-<italic>social functioning</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.650 / -; SF-36-<italic>pain</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.128 / -; SF-36-<italic>general health</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Yeni, Tulek and Terzi, 2022&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>December 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Neurology outpatient clinic of a University Hospital</p><p>Turkey</p><p>Europe and Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>89</p><p>41.1&#x000a0;years</p><p>56 female; 33 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>262</p><p>38.1&#x000a0;years</p><p>135 female; 127 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / BDI / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / 0.39 (0.14 to 0.63)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / WAQ / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / 0.35 ( 0.11 to 0.59)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Sleep quality / PSQI / <italic>p</italic> 0.906 / 0.01 (-0.23 to 0.25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Bonavita et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>April 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Web-based (unspecific)</p><p>Italy</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>612</p><p>43.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>465 female; 147 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>674</p><p>44.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>490 female; 184 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / PHQ / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -</p><p>(1) Stress / PSS / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Costabile et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between April to May 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Web-based (unspecific)</p><p>Italy</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>497</p><p>42.4&#x000a0;years</p><p>351 female; 146 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>348</p><p>40.8&#x000a0;years</p><p>264 female; 84 male</p></td><td align="left">(1) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / NeuroQoL-<italic>cognitive disfunction</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 / 0.50 (0.37 to 0.64); NeuroQoL-<italic>abstraction and logical abilities</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.1 / -0.34 (-0.48 to -0.21); NeuroQoL-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.005 / 0.25 (0.12 to 0.39); NeuroQoL-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.064 / 0.20 (0.06 to 0.34); NeuroQoL-<italic>emotional dyscontrol</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.015 / 0.21 (0.07 to 0.35); NeuroQoL-<italic>sleep disturbances</italic> / p 0.017 / 0.22 (0.08 to 0.36)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Garjani et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between May to July 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Laboratory database (United Kingdom MS Register)</p><p>United Kingdom</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>2010</p><p>56.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>1488 female; 522 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>380</p><p>49.0&#x000a0;years</p><p>248 female; 132</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / PHQ / <italic>p</italic> 0.002 / -</p><p>(1) Anxiety / GAD / <italic>p</italic> 0.081 / -</p><p>(1) Stress / IES-R / <italic>p</italic> 0.52 / -</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Shaygannejad, Afshari-Safavi and Hatef, 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between March to April 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Kashani Hospital</p><p>Iran</p><p>Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>McDonald&#x02019;s</p><p>223</p><p>35.9&#x000a0;years</p><p>183 female; 40 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>245</p><p>34.2&#x000a0;years</p><p>185 female; 60 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / DASS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.054 / 0.36 (0.17 to 0.54)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / DASS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.080 / 0.36 (0.18 to 0.54)</p><p>(1) Stress / DASS-<italic>stress</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.011 / 0.38 (0.20 to 0.56)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Stojanov et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between April to May 2020</p><p>-</p><p>Laboratory database</p><p>Republic of Serbia</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>McDonald&#x02019;s</p><p>67</p><p>45.1&#x000a0;years</p><p>45 female; 22 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>85</p><p>44.2&#x000a0;years</p><p>56 female; 29 male</p></td><td align="left">(1) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Sleep quality / PSQI / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 / 1.74 (1.36 to 2.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Motolese et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between April to May 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Policlinico Universitario Campus Bio-Medico</p><p>Italy</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>-</p><p>60</p><p>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;years (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;40);&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;years (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</p><p>41 female; 19 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>50</p><p>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;years (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;34);&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;years (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;16)</p><p>31 female; 19 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / BDI-<italic>total</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.010 / 0.33 (-0.05 to 0.70); BDI-<italic>neuroveg</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.006 / 0.44 (0.06 to 0.82); BDI-<italic>cognitive</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.152 / 0.26 (-0.12 to 0.64)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / GAD / <italic>p</italic> 0.0331 / -0.31 (-0.69 to 0.07)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) Sleep quality / PSQI / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / 0.67 (0.28 to 1.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Stojanov et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>April 2020</p><p>-</p><p>Laboratory database</p><p>Republic of Serbia</p><p>Europe</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>McDonald&#x02019;s</p><p>95</p><p>43.4&#x000a0;years</p><p>64 female; 31 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>99</p><p>44.3&#x000a0;years</p><p>66 female; 33 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / HAM-D / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 / 2.08 (1.73 to 2.43)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / HAM-A / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 / 1.84 (1.50 to 2.18)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) Quality of life / MSQoL-54-<italic>mental health</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 / -1.57 (-1.89 to -1.25); MSQoL-54-<italic>physical health</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 / -2.31 (-2.67 to -1.94)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Talaat et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>Between March to April 2020</p><p>Online</p><p>Alexandria University Hospital</p><p>Egypt</p><p>Africa and Asia</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>MS</p><p>McDonald&#x02019;s</p><p>115</p><p>34.4&#x000a0;years</p><p>89 female; 26 male</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="3"><p>129</p><p>31.7&#x000a0;years</p><p>93 female; 36 male</p></td><td align="left"><p>(1) Depression / DASS-<italic>depression</italic> / <italic>p</italic> 0.001 / 0.54 (0.28 to 0.79)</p><p>(1) Anxiety / DASS-<italic>anxiety</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 0.40 (0.15 to 0.66)</p><p>(1) Stress / DASS-<italic>stress</italic> / <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 / 1.01 (0.75 to 1.28)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2) -</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3) -</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>PD</italic> Parkinson&#x02019;s disease, <italic>MS</italic> Multiple Sclerosis, <italic>MDS</italic> Movement Disorder Society, <italic>UKPDSBB</italic> United Kingdom Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease Society Brain Bank, <italic>n</italic> sample size, <italic>BAI</italic> Beck Anxiety Inventory-II, <italic>BDI</italic> Beck Depression Inventory, <italic>DASS</italic> Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale, <italic>FACT-7</italic> Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-7, <italic>GAD</italic> Generalized Anxiety Disorder, <italic>HADS</italic> Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, <italic>HAM-A</italic> Hamilton Anxiety Scale, <italic>HAM-D</italic> Hamilton Depression Scale, <italic>IES-R</italic> Impact of Event Scale-Revised, <italic>ISI</italic> Insomnia Severity Index, <italic>MSQoL-54</italic> Multiple Sclerosis Quality of Life-54 Instrument, <italic>NeuroQoL</italic> Quality of Life in Neurological Disorders, <italic>PDQ-39</italic> Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire-39, <italic>PHQ</italic> Patient Health Questionnaire, <italic>PSQI</italic> Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, <italic>PSS</italic> Perceived Stress Scale, <italic>SF-8</italic> Short Form of Quality of Life-8, <italic>SF-36</italic> Short Form of Quality of Life-36, <italic>WAQ</italic> Worry and Anxiety Questionnaire</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par37">Seven studies were performed in individuals with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Of these, three studies defined the diagnostic criterion with the two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] using the United Kingdom Parkinson&#x02019;s Disease Society Brain Bank [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]&#x000a0;and one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] using the Movement Disorder Society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The remaining four studies did not report this information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The selected studies totaled a sample of 627 individuals with PD. The mean age was 65.0 (range 55.0 to 72.3). According to the studies that reported biological sex as a variable, 241 of 478 individuals were female (50.4%) and 237 were male (49.6%). One study did not report biological sex of its participants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Regarding healthy controls, a total of 857 individuals were used as comparators. According to the studies that reported age (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;413) and biological sex (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;364) as a variable, the mean age was 65.2&#x000a0;years (range 55.5 to 78) with 198 being female (54.4%) and 166 being male (45.6%). One study did not report the mean age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and two studies did not report the biological sex of its participants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">Eleven studies were performed in individuals with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Four studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] defined the diagnostic criterion according to the McDonald's criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Seven studies did not report this information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The selected studies totaled a sample of 3923 individuals with MS. Of 3863 individuals, the mean age was 42.7 (range 34.4 to 48.1). One study did not report the mean age of the individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Of 3854 individuals, 2839 were women (73.7%) and 1015 were men (26.3%). In another study, information on the biological sex of individuals was not available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Regarding healthy controls, 2432 individuals were used as comparators. Of 2382 individuals, the mean age was 40.7 (range 31.7 to 44.3). One study did not report the mean age of its participants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. From a total of 2432 individuals, 1690 were female (69.5%) and 742 male (30.5%).</p><p id="Par39">Fifteen studies investigated neuropsychiatric disorders (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;seven [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]; MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;eight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]). Thirteen studies investigated depression (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;five [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]; and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;eight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]). The following measures were implemented to assess depression in individuals with PD: 1) Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale (DASS) (depression domain), 2) Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) (depression domain), and 3) Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ); and in individuals with MS: 1) Beck Depression Inventory, 2) DASS (depression domain), 3) Hamilton Depression Scale, and 4) PHQ. Thirteen studies investigated anxiety (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;six [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;seven [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]). The following measures were implemented to assess depression in individuals with PD: 1) Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI), 2) DASS (anxiety domain), 3) Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD), and 4) HADS (anxiety domain); and in individuals with MS: 1) BAI, 2) DASS (anxiety domain), 3) GAD, 4) Hamilton Anxiety Scale, and 5) Worry and Anxiety Questionnaire. Six studies investigated stress (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;four [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]). Studies in individuals with PD assessed stress via 1) DASS (stress domain), and 2) Perceived Stress Scale (PSS); and studies in individuals with MS assessed stress via 1) DASS (stress domain), 2) Impact of Event Scale-Revised, and 3) PSS.</p><p id="Par40">Six studies investigated sleep disorders (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;four [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]). Five studies analyzed sleep quality (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;four [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]) through the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. One study analyzed insomnia in individuals with PD and used the Insomnia Severity Index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. It was not possible to synthesize scientific evidence for insomnia based on the results.</p><p id="Par41">Six studies investigated quality of life (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;four [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]). The Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire-39 and Short Form of Quality of Life-8 were used to assess quality of life in individuals with PD; and the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-7, Quality of Life in Neurological Disorders, Multiple Sclerosis Quality of Life-54 Instrument, and Short Form of Quality of life-36 for individuals with MS.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation, and data analysis</title><p id="Par42">Individuals with PD presented significantly higher levels of depression (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02 to 0.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;44% [moderate heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;2.1) and stress (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32 to 0.87,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0% [low heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;2.2). No significant changes were observed for the anxiety (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for limitations (risk of bias), inconsistency and indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.08 to 1.36, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.08 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;2.3). The forest plots for the grouped studies in individuals with PD is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The forest plots for the grouped studies in individuals with Parkinson's disease for depression, stress, and anxiety</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2023_3176_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">Individuals with MS showed significantly higher levels of depression (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.20 to 1.26,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;3.1), higher levels of stress (low quality of evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07 to 1.31,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;93% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;3.2), and lower quality of life (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.21 to 1.32,<italic> p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;89% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;3.3). No significant changes were observed for the anxiety (very low quality of evidence [downgraded for indirectness], SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.53 [moderate effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.01 to 1.06, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05 and<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;3.4) and sleep quality (low quality of evidence, SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.80 [large effect], 95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.23 to 1.82, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13 and <italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;97% [high heterogeneity]) (Fig.&#x000a0;3.5). The forest plots for the grouped studies in individuals with MS is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The quality of evidence and strength of recommendation, and the interpretation of the GRADE domains are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The forest plots for the grouped studies in individuals with Multiple Sclerosis for depression, stress, quality of life, anxiety, and sleep quality</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2023_3176_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of the GRADE approach</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Outcomes</th><th align="left">(1)</th><th align="left">(2)</th><th align="left">(3)</th><th align="left">(4)</th><th align="left">(5)</th><th align="left">Studies</th><th align="left" colspan="2">N&#x000b0; of participants (Diseases <italic>vs</italic> Health controls) / N&#x000b0; of studies</th><th align="left"><sup>*</sup>Effect size</th><th align="left">Quality of the evidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Depression</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Shalash et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</p><p>Xia et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">189</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02 to 0.77</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;44% (moderate heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(two studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Blakemore et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</p><p>Shalash et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">187</td><td align="left">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32 to 0.87</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0% (low heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(two studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>A</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>B</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Salari et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</p><p>Shalash et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</p><p>Xia et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">294</td><td align="left">631</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.08 to 1.36</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.08</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x025ef;&#x025ef;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(three studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Multiple Sclerosis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Depression</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Yeni, Tulek and Terzi, 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</p><p>Shaygannejad, Afshari-Safavi and Hatef, 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</p><p>Motolese et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</p><p>Stojanov et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p><p>Talaat et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">582</td><td align="left">785</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.20 to 1.26</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very Low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(five studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Shaygannejad, Afshari-Safavi and Hatef, 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</p><p>Talaat et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">338</td><td align="left">334</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07 to 1.31</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;93% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;</p><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(two studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Quality of life</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Goverover et al. 2022&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</p><p>Costabile et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">566</td><td align="left">443</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.21 to 1.32</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;89% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very Low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(two studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Anxiety</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">S<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Yeni, Tulek and Terzi, 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</p><p>Shaygannejad, Afshari-Safavi and Hatef, 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</p><p>Motolese et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</p><p>Stojanov et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p><p>Talaat et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">582</td><td align="left">785</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.53 (moderate effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.01 to 1.06</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x025ef;</p><p>Very Low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(five studies)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">&#x02003;Sleep quality</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Yeni, Tulek and Terzi, 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</p><p>Stojanov et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</p><p>Motolese et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</p></td><td align="left">216</td><td align="left">397</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.80 (large effect)</p><p>95% CI&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.23 to 1.82</p><p><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13</p><p><italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;97% (high heterogeneity)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;&#x02a01;</p><p>Low</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">(three studies)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SMD</italic> standardized mean differences, <italic>95% CI</italic> 95% of confidence interval, <italic>I2</italic> consistency between the studies</p><p>(1) Limitations (risk of bias); (2) Inconsistency; (3) Indirectness; (4) Imprecision; (5) Publication bias; (Ns) No serious; (S) Serious; A Downgrading due to&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;75% of the studies presented low risk of bias; B Downgrading due to different directions towards the results found; C Downgrading due to heterogeneity of the scales for evaluating measures of results; D Downgrading due to was sparse data with less than 200 individuals per comparison; E Downgrading if&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50% of the studies are from the same research team</p><p><sup>*</sup>Cohen's criteria: small effect (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.20), moderate effect (between 0.21 and 0.79) or large effect (&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.80)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Risk of bias</title><p id="Par44">The final score for the 18 studies included in the customized checklist of Downs and Black ranged from eight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] to 12 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The average score was 10.5. Seventeen studies had a low risk of bias (94.4%). Three items presented percentages below 75% and were the least attended (3, 9, and 26). Of the 18 studies included, 13 (27.8%) did not meet item 26 (internal validity), 11 (38.9%) did not meet item 3 (reporting&#x02014;patients included), and 11 (38.9%) did not meet item 9 (reporting&#x02014;patients lost). The score for the 18 included studies is presented in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Customized downs and black checklist for bias risk assessment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Author (years)</th><th align="left" colspan="7"><bold>Reporting</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>External Validity</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="2"><bold>Internal Validity (bias)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Internal Validity&#x02014;Confounding (selection bias)</bold></th><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">(1)</th><th align="left">(2)</th><th align="left">(3)</th><th align="left">(6)</th><th align="left">(7)</th><th align="left">(9)</th><th align="left">(10)</th><th align="left">(11)</th><th align="left">(18)</th><th align="left">(20)</th><th align="left">(21)</th><th align="left">(22)</th><th align="left">(26)</th><th align="left">Total score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Balci et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*12/13</p><p>92.3%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Koc et al. 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Yeni, Tulek and Terzi, 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Blakemore et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bonavita et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Costabile et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Garjani et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kitani-Morii et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Suzuki et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Motolese et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Talaat et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xia et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*11/13</p><p>84.6%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shaygannejad, Afshari-Safavi and Hatef, 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*10/13</p><p>76.9%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stojanov et al. 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*10/13</p><p>76.9%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shalash et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*10/13</p><p>76.9%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Stojanov et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*10/13</p><p>76.9%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Goverover et al. 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>*9/13</p><p>69.2%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Salari et al. 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"><p>8/13</p><p>61.5%</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Studies which answered the criteria (%)</td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>7/18</p><p>38.9%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>7/18</p><p>38.9%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>14/18</p><p>77.8%</p></td><td align="left"><p>18/18</p><p>100%</p></td><td align="left"><p>15/18</p><p>83.3%</p></td><td align="left"><p>16/18</p><p>88.9%</p></td><td align="left"><p>5/18</p><p>27.8%</p></td><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: (0) No / Unable to determine; (1) Yes</p><p>(1) Is the hypothesis/aim/objective of the study clearly described? (2) Are the main outcomes to be measured clearly described in the Introduction or Methods section? (3) Are the characteristics of the patients included in the study clearly described? (6) Are the main findings of the study clearly described? (7) Does the study provide estimates of the random variability in the data for the main outcomes? (9) Have the characteristics of patients lost to follow&#x02010;up been described? (10) Have actual probability values been reported (e.g., 0.035 rather than&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 for the main outcomes except Where the probability value is less than 0.001? (11) Were the subjects asked to participate in the study representative of the entire population from which they were recruited? (18) Were the statistical tests used to assess the main outcomes appropriate? (20) Were the main outcome measures used accurate (valid and reliable)? (21) Were the patients in different intervention groups (trials and cohort studies) or were the cases and controls (case&#x02010;control studies) recruited from the same population? (22) Were study subjects in different intervention groups (trials and cohort studies) or were the cases and controls (case&#x02010;control studies) recruited over the same period of time? (26) Were losses of patients to follow&#x02010;up taken into account?</p><p><sup>*</sup>High methodological quality (score&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;9 [&#x02265;&#x02009;66.8%])</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par45">This systematic review and meta-analysis investigated the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on neuropsychiatric disorders, sleep disorders, and quality of life in individuals with PD, MS, and AD compared to healthy controls. The results showed the negative repercussion of the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with PD and MS. Both individuals with PD and MS presented higher levels of depression and stress. Additionally, individuals with MS presented lower quality of life compared to healthy controls. It was not possible to synthesize scientific evidence of the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with AD.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>Parkinson&#x02019;s disease</title><p id="Par46">Individuals with PD had significantly elevated levels of depression during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy control (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04). The quality of the evidence was very low. The size of the effect was moderate (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.40). This comparison group presented moderate heterogeneity (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;44%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. It is estimated that about 25% of the meta-analysis present values of<italic> I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> above 50% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Even though the heterogeneity of this comparison group was below 50%, this result should be analyzed with caution.</p><p id="Par47">Before the COVID-19 pandemic, depression was the fourth most prevalent neuropsychiatric disorder in individuals with PD when compared to healthy controls (36.6% and 14.9%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Therefore, the identification of high levels of depression during the COVID-19 pandemic highlights the need for improved clinical management of depression in this population considering that this neuropsychiatric disorder is treatable. The literature shows that pharmacological (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors) and non-pharmacological (aerobic physical activity and cognitive behavioral therapy) treatments have the potential to alleviate depression in these individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">On the other hand, individuals with PD did not present high levels of anxiety (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.08) during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls. The quality of the evidence was very low. A high heterogeneity (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95%) was identified in this comparison group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In part, this high heterogeneity may be due to the different directions of the statistical results and effect sizes observed among the analyzed studies. Additionally, this analysis presented a study with moderate risk of bias potentially influencing the results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">Different delivery methods were also implemented for the measures of anxiety (i.e., interview or self-report) which have been previously reported to potentially interfere with anxiety outcomes in individuals with PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Two studies were delivered online (self-report) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and one study by telephone (interview) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. One could hypothesize that such differences in the delivery methods observed in the included studies may have influenced the results by the potential underestimation of the participant&#x02019;s condition in a self-reported method versus a more in-depth analysis when the interview is conducted by a trained evaluator.</p><p id="Par50">Individuals with PD had significantly higher levels of stress during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The quality of the evidence was very low with a moderate effect size (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60). This comparison group presented homogeneous results (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Stress was evaluated by two different scales (Perceived Stress Scale and Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale) in the included studies suggesting that the use of different types of scales to assess stress in these individuals does not seem to interfere with the results.</p><p id="Par51">Stress plays an important role in the development of depression in individuals with PD and has been shown to act as a key element influencing its pathophysiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Although we cannot establish the relationship between stress and depression during the COVID-19 pandemic in these individuals, it is important to highlight that this systematic review and meta-analysis identified high levels of these two neuropsychiatric disorders. In addition to its contribution to depression in individuals with PD, stress can also contribute to the worsening of motor symptoms with the progression of PD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Therefore, the identification of stress during the COVID-19 pandemic in this population is of great importance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Multiple sclerosis</title><p id="Par52">Individuals with MS had significantly elevated levels of depression during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007). The quality of the evidence was very low with a moderate effect size (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.73). However, a high heterogeneity was identified in this comparison group (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. One study did not observe a significant increase in depression in individuals with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Therefore, the different statistical results do not seem to be the main reason for the high heterogeneity. In part, we hypothesize that the observed high heterogeneity may be due to the different scales used to assess depression in this population.</p><p id="Par53">A systematic review and meta-analysis study conducted before the COVID-19 pandemic observed a high prevalence of depression in individuals with MS (30.5%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. A high heterogeneity was identified in this study (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;99.4%). Therefore, it seems that systematic reviews and meta-analysis studies that report higher levels of depression in these individuals also identify high heterogeneity. The identification of high levels of depression during the COVID-19 pandemic in this population is of great importance since psychological and pharmacological treatments for depression in individuals with MS have been shown to be effective in reducing depressive symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">On the other hand, individuals with MS did not present high levels of anxiety (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05) during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls. The quality of the evidence was very low, and a high heterogeneity was identified in this comparison group (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. It is important to highlight that in an included study, healthy individuals had higher levels of anxiety compared to individuals with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In part, we hypothesize that this result may be one of the reasons for the observed high heterogeneity in this comparison group.</p><p id="Par55">Previous literature has shown the high prevalence of anxiety in individuals with MS before the COVID-19 pandemic (22.1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. However, the same was not identified in our systematic review and meta-analysis during the COVID-19 pandemic. The included studies used four different types of scales to assess anxiety which may have influenced the outcome. A study developed and evaluated the psychometric properties of the specific Coronavirus Anxiety Scale to assess the pandemic-associated anxiety of COVID-19. This scale was shown to be reliable and valid for scientific research and clinical practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, to our knowledge, its application has not been tested in individuals with MS and PD. We encourage that future studies in different populations standardize the use of the Coronavirus Anxiety Scale; therefore, facilitating its comparative use across studies.</p><p id="Par56">Individuals with MS had significantly higher levels of stress during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03). The quality of the evidence was low with a moderate effect size (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69). It is important to highlight that this comparison group met all the criteria for the GRADE approach reinforcing the quality and strength of the recommendation of this scientific evidence. However, high heterogeneity was identified in this comparison group (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;95%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The included studies used the Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale to assess stress. However, the observed effect sizes varied between large [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and moderate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] partly justifying the high heterogeneity.</p><p id="Par57">An additional factor that can justify this high heterogeneity is the temporal structure of MS, that is, whether stress assessment was performed at the beginning or during progressive states of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. For this reason, stress is the neuropsychiatric disorder with the greatest observed controversy in studies conducted before the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. However, there is strong scientific evidence of the association between stress and progression of MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], which highlights the importance of identifying the increase in stress during the COVID-19 pandemic in this population. Thus, stress management strategies such as breathing and muscle relaxation techniques that have shown benefits in these individuals should be implemented as part of the treatment strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p id="Par58">Regarding sleep, individuals with MS did not present low sleep quality during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13). The quality of the evidence was low. Although no significant difference in effect size has been identified, this comparison group met all the criteria for the GRADE approach. A high heterogeneity was identified in this comparison group (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;97%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The studies used the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index to assess sleep quality. Although these studies used the same evaluation scale, the direction of statistical results and effect sizes were different, which in part may have contributed to the observed high heterogeneity.</p><p id="Par59">Restless leg syndrome or Willis-Ekbom's disease and sleep apnea were the most investigated sleep disorders in individuals with MS before the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. During the COVID-19 pandemic, sleep quality was investigated in three studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]&#x000a0;of which none investigated insomnia. This result identifies that some of the major sleep disorders (i.e., insomnia) may have been overlooked in this population during the COVID-19 pandemic. This result was observed by a systematic review study conducted before the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. In addition, it is important to highlight that poor sleep quality is related to lower quality of life observed in this population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">Individuals with MS presented lower quality of life during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to healthy controls (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006). The quality of the evidence was very low with a moderate effect size (SMD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77); however, high heterogeneity was identified in this comparison group (<italic>I</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;89%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Different scales were used to assess quality of life and the effect sizes differed between studies. In part, these methodological and results differences among the studies included in this meta-analysis may justify the observed high heterogeneity.</p><p id="Par61">The World Health Organization during the COVID-19 pandemic instituted a series of strict measures to contain the advance of SARS-CoV-2, such as social distancing and quarantine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These measures caused a broad, substantial, and lasting psychological impact worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], which may be intrinsically associated with the observed low quality of life of individuals with MS during the COVID-19 pandemic. Furthermore, a systematic review study conducted before the COVID-19 pandemic observed that psychosocial, clinical, and demographic factors are important determinants of low quality of life in these individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], reinforcing the hypothetical association between the healthcare measures implemented to contain the spread of SARS-CoV-2 and lower levels of quality of life in these individuals. Gil-Gonz&#x000e1;lez and colleagues (2020) also identified that among various neuropsychiatric disorders, depression and anxiety were associated with lower quality of life in individuals with MS prior to the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Therefore, the significantly higher levels of depression found in our analysis may have also contributed to the lower quality of life observed in this population.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Alzheimer's disease</title><p id="Par62">No study in individuals with AD met the inclusion criteria for this systematic review and meta-analysis. We hypothesize that two factors could be the main drivers for such results. First, even though the impact of COVID-19 has been investigated in individuals with dementia of various etiologies, many of the studies were limited by a lack of comparison to healthy controls. Such limitation makes it difficult to draw conclusions that are specific to the disease being studied which could potentially skew the outcome analysis in this systematic review and meta-analysis. Therefore, studies lacking a control group with healthy participants were excluded. Second, most of the assessments used for neuropsychiatric disorders, sleep disorders and quality of life in individuals with AD rely on the caregiver's report potentially adding an additional layer of subjectivity and hindering the conductance of studies of this nature.</p><p id="Par63">Hughes, Liu and Baumbach (2021) study has reported a negative impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on individuals with dementia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. An interruption of daily activities has also been associated with the onset or worsening of neuropsychiatric disorders, such as depression, and anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]; therefore, it is important that future rigorous studies quantify these disorders in individuals with dementia, including AD to implement strategies that target the symptoms associated with disease progression as well as to investigate their impact on measures of quality of life in this population. In addition, previous evidence suggests the prevalence of depression and anxiety in caregivers of individuals with dementia during the COVID-19 pandemic highlighting the importance of more rigorous studies not only for this population, but for their caregivers as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Methodological considerations</title><p id="Par64">Eight scientific measures were synthesized and assessed based on the GRADE approach (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;three and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;five). Although the quality of two measures in individuals with MS were low (stress and sleep quality), it is important to highlight that the comparison groups met all the criteria for the GRADE approach. However, the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation in systematic review studies and meta-analysis of observational studies begin as low quality and not at high quality as observed in randomized clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par65">In other scientific measures (PD&#x02009;=&#x02009;anxiety, depression, and stress and MS&#x02009;=&#x02009;depression, anxiety, and quality of life), the main criterion responsible for lowering the quality of evidence to &#x0201c;very low&#x0201d; was indirectness related to the heterogeneity of the scales used to evaluate the outcomes. Therefore, we recommend that future studies standardize scales for the evaluation of neuropsychiatric disorders and quality of life as a way to increase the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation.</p><p id="Par66">It is also important to highlight that in the included studies, three items were the least attended according to the customized checklist of Downs and Black for the risk of bias assessment. Items 3 and 9 refer to &#x0201c;reporting&#x0201d; and item 26 refers to &#x0201c;internal validity&#x0201d;. Therefore, we recommend that future studies better describe the sample inclusion and exclusion criteria, as well as justifying and reporting the proportions of follow-up losses in order to reduce the risk of bias in observational studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="Par67">Strengths: 1) The originality of the theme, given that the COVID-19 pandemic generated a significant and immeasurable impact on the population worldwide; 2) The target population, given the high prevalence of chronic neurodegenerative and demyelinating diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] such as PD, MS, and AD; 3) The outcomes, since the identification of neuropsychiatric disorders and sleep disorders allows the implementation of the best treatment strategies, reflecting on the better quality of life of these populations; and 4) The methodology, given that it followed PRISMA guidelines, recommendations of the Cochrane Collaboration, the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation by the GRADE approach, the risk of bias of the included studies by the customized checklist of Downs and Black, and the protocol was registered in PROSPERO.</p><p id="Par68">Limitations: 1) The stages of PD disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] were not defined as an inclusion criteria and there was no distinction between the main types of MS possibly due to the difficulties and challenges of remote research with these populations during the COVID-19 pandemic; 2) Only observational studies were included, which does not allow cause-effect relationships to be established between the COVID-19 pandemic and outcomes investigated; 3) Based on the GRADE approach, the systematic review and meta-analysis studies of observational studies began as low quality of evidence due to a higher risk of bias, hindering the generalization of our results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; and 4) The limitations of qualitative research, such as the accuracy of the information collected and subjectivity of the analyses due to the interpretations of the authors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par69">In general, the COVID-19 pandemic negatively impacted in individuals with PD and MS. Individuals with PD and MS had significantly higher levels of depression and stress compared to healthy controls. Individuals with MS showed a lower quality of life compared to healthy controls. On the other hand, the COVID-19 pandemic did not seem to have significant repercussions on anxiety in individuals with PD and MS, and sleep quality in individuals with MS when compared to healthy controls. Further studies are needed to investigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic in individuals with AD and sleep disorders (e.g., insomnia). Future studies should prioritize the standardization of the scales for the assessment of neuropsychiatric disorders and quality of life in individuals with PD and MS to increase the quality of evidence and strength of the recommendation.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AD</term><def><p id="Par5">Alzheimer's disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAI</term><def><p id="Par6">Beck Anxiety Inventory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par7">Confidence intervals</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par8">Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DASS</term><def><p id="Par9">Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GAD</term><def><p id="Par10">Generalized Anxiety Disorder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRADE</term><def><p id="Par11">Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development, and Evaluation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HADS</term><def><p id="Par12">Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p id="Par13">Multiple Sclerosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PD</term><def><p id="Par14">Parkinson's disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHQ</term><def><p id="Par15">Patient Health Questionnaire</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PICO</term><def><p id="Par16">Patient, Intervention, Comparison, and Outcome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSS</term><def><p id="Par17">Perceived Stress Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRISMA</term><def><p id="Par18">Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta Analyses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PROSPERO</term><def><p id="Par19">Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p id="Par20">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMD</term><def><p id="Par21">Standardized mean differences</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the funding provided by Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (CAPES), Brazil, Finance Code 001.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to the article conception and design. Material preparation, data collection and analysis were performed by Marcos Paulo Braz de Oliveira, Ana Em&#x000ed;lia Fonseca de Castro and Andressa Let&#x000ed;cia Miri. The first draft of the article was written by Marcos Paulo Braz de Oliveira and all authors commented on previous versions of the study. All authors read and approved the final article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship and/or publication of this article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par70">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par71">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par72">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Statement on the second meeting of the international health regulations (2005) emergency committee regarding the outbreak of novel coronav&#x000ed;rus (2019-nCoV). 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/30-01-2020-statement-on-the-second-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-outbreak-of-novel-coronavirus-(2019-ncov">https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/30-01-2020-statement-on-the-second-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-outbreak-of-novel-coronavirus-(2019-ncov</ext-link>). Accessed 15 Mar 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Virology, epidemiology, pathogenesis, and control of COVID-19</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>372</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v12040372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32230900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chronic diseases as a predictor for severity and mortality of COVID-19: a systematic review with cumulative meta-analysis</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>588013</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.588013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34540855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vimal</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tandon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongyi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurodegenerative disorders of Alzheimer, Parkinsonism, Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis and Multiple Sclerosis: an early diagnostic approach for precision treatment</article-title><source>Metab Brain Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11011-021-00800-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34719771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erkkinen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Geschwind</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical neurology and epidemiology of the major neurodegenerative diseases</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>a033118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a033118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28716886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Torsney</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kouli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Torsney</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: etiology, neuropathology, and pathogenesis</article-title><source>Parkinson&#x02019;s disease: pathogenesis and clinical aspects</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Brisbane</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Codon Publications</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sclerosis: pathology, diagnosis and treatments</article-title><source>Exp Ther Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3163</fpage><lpage>3166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2017.4410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Atluri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yndart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease: pathogenesis, diagnostics, and therapeutics</article-title><source>Int J Nanomedicine</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>5541</fpage><lpage>5554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S200490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31410002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferini-Strambi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Salsone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and neurological disorders: are neurodegenerative or neuroimmunological diseases more vulnerable?</article-title><source>J Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-020-10070-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32696341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cummings JL, Diaz C, Levy M, Binetti G, I Litvan I. Neuropsychiatric syndromes in neurodegenerative disease: frequency and signficance. Semin Clin Neuropsychiatry. 1996;1:241&#x02013;47.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of quality of life in neurodegenerative disorders</article-title><source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-001-0088-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11898540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurodegenerative disorders and sleep</article-title><source>Sleep Med Clin</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2017.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29412984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iodice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect neurological, cognitive, and behavioral effects of COVID-19 on the healthy elderly, mild-cognitive-impairment, and Alzheimer's disease populations</article-title><source>Neurol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-020-04902-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33409824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social and psychological impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on people with Parkinson's disease: a scoping review</article-title><source>Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34571441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abasiyanik</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahraman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and physical activity behaviour in people with neurological diseases: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Dev Phys Disabil.</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10882-022-09836-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35125854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title><source>Int J Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>105906</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2021.105906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33789826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions</source><year>2019</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GRADE: an emerging consensus on rating quality of evidence and strength of recommendations</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2008</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.39489.470347.AD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobre</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jatene</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence based clinical practice. part 1 - well structured clinical questions</article-title><source>Rev Assoc Med Bras</source><year>2003</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-42302003000400039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14963600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobre</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jatene</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence-based clinical practice.&#x000a0;part II&#x02013; searching evidence databases</article-title><source>Rev Assoc Med Bras</source><year>2004</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>08</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-42302004000100045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15253037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamboni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using GQM and TAM to evaluate StArt - a tool that supports systematic review</article-title><source>CLEI Electr J</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Olkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><source>Statistical Methods for Meta-analysis</source><year>1985</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The feasibility of creating a checklist for the assessment of the methodological quality both of randomised and non-randomised studies of health care interventions</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>1998</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.52.6.377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9764259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanardi</surname><given-names>APJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gait parameters of Parkinson's disease compared with healthy controls: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>752</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-80768-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33436993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Montori</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GRADE guidelines: 5. rating the quality of evidence - publication bias</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2011.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21802904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The concepts of power analysis</article-title><source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Inc</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses testing for heterogeneity</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2003</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashrafi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of anxiety in Parkinson's disease during the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1095</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.28116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32395849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roushdy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Essam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental health, physical activity, and quality of life in Parkinson's disease during COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1099</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.28134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32428342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation on sleep and mental health of patients with Parkinson's disease during the Coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic</article-title><source>Sleep Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aktar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Buran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colakoglu</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on physical activity, anxiety, and depression in patients with Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Int J Rehabil Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MRR.0000000000000460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33653991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blakemore</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>K-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Higher perceived stress and exacerbated motor symptoms in Parkinson's disease during the COVID-19 lockdown in New Zealand</article-title><source>N Z Med J</source><year>2021</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34239144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitani-Morii</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for neuropsychiatric symptoms in patients with Parkinson's disease during COVID-19 pandemic in Japan</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e0245864</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0245864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Numao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Komagamine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the quality of life of patients with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease and their caregivers: a single-center survey in Tochigi prefecture</article-title><source>J Parkinsons Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JPD-212560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33780375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motolese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albergo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The psychological impact of COVID-19 pandemic on people with Multiple Sclerosis</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>580507</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2020.580507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33193033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malobabic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Milosevic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psychological status of patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis during coronavirus disease-2019 outbreak</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><year>2020</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>102407</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2020.102407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32702641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talaat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are multiple sclerosis patients and their caregivers more anxious and more committed to following the basic preventive measures during the COVID-19 pandemic?</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><year>2020</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>102580</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2020.102580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33296977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonavita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparaco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Borriello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavorgna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceived stress and social support in a large population of people with multiple sclerosis recruited online through the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Eur J Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3396</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.14697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33368849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costabile</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carotenuto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavorgna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic and mental distress in multiple sclerosis: Implications for clinical management</article-title><source>Eur J Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3375</fpage><lpage>3383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.14580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33043560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garjani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental health of people with multiple sclerosis during the COVID-19 outbreak: a prospective cohort and cross-sectional case-control study of the UK MS register</article-title><source>Mult Scler</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/13524585211020435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34080892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaygannejad</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Afshari-Safavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of mental health, knowledge, and attitude of patients with multiple sclerosis and neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder in response to 2019 novel coronavirus</article-title><source>Neurol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2891</fpage><lpage>2901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-020-04905-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33219424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vojinovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stojanov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality of sleep and fatigue in patients with the relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis during the coronavirus disease-2019 pandemic</article-title><source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source><year>2021</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>106640</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2021.106640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33901751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goverover</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Botticello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationships between changes in daily occupations and health-related quality of life in persons with multiple sclerosis during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><year>2022</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>103339</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2021.103339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35158428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Koc ER, Demir AB, Topaloglu E, Turan OF, Ozkaya G. Effects of quarantine applied during the COVID-19 pandemic on
mental health and quality of life in patients with multiple sclerosis and healthy controls. Neurol Sci. 2022;43:2263&#x02013;69.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilford</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of clinical diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease: a clinico-pathological study of 100 cases</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><year>1992</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.55.3.181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1564476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilford</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of clinical diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease: a clinico-pathological study of 100 cases</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry.</source><year>1992</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.55.3.181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1564476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postuma</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MDS clinical diagnostic criteria for Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Mov Disord</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1591</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.26424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26474316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Compston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recommended diagnostic criteria for multiple sclerosis: guidelines from the international panel on the diagnosis of multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.1032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11456302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Meta-analyses on prevalence of selected Parkinson's nonmotor symptoms before and after diagnosis</article-title><source>Transl Neurodegener</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2047-9158-4-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25671103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starkstein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of depression in Parkinson's disease: a systematic review</article-title><source>Mov Disord Clin Pract</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mdc3.12507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30363415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of physical activity on patients with depression and Parkinson's disease: a systematic review</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0181515</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28749970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmerle</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Seroogy</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress, depression and Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>2012</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2011.09.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22001159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dall&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mabandla</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early life stress, depression and Parkinson's disease: a new approach</article-title><source>Mol Brain</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13041-018-0356-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29551090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boeschoten</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Braamse</surname><given-names>AMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beekman</surname><given-names>ATF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of depression and anxiety in Multiple Sclerosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2016.11.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28017241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiest</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of interventions for depression and anxiety in persons with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2015.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26856938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus anxiety scale: a brief mental health screener for COVID-19 related anxiety</article-title><source>Death Stud</source><year>2020</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07481187.2020.1748481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32299304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briones-Buixassa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mil&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aragon&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bufill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrufat</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress and multiple sclerosis: a systematic review considering potential moderating and mediating factors and methods of assessing stress</article-title><source>Health Psychol Open</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2055102915612271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2055102915612271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artemiadis</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vervainioti</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexopoulos</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anagnostouli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Darviri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress management and multiple sclerosis: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Arch Clin Neuropsychol</source><year>2012</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/arclin/acs039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22491729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marrie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the incidence and prevalence of sleep disorders and seizure disorders in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Mult Scler</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458514564486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25533301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bamer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Amtmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of sleep problems in individuals with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Mult Scler</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458508092807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18632776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: rapid review of the evidence</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>395</volume><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30460-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-San-Gregorio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in adults with multiple sclerosis: a systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e041249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-041249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33257490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of COVID-19 on the health and well-being of informal caregivers of people with dementia: a rapid systematic review</article-title><source>Gerontol Geriatr Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>23337214211020164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/23337214211020164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34104687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simonetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychiatric symptoms in elderly with dementia during COVID-19 pandemic: definition, treatment, and future directions</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>579842</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.579842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33132939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoehn</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahr</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parkinsonism: onset, progression and mortality</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>1967</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.17.5.427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6067254</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>